A Guide to the Taylor Family Papers, 1686-1890
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Taylor Family Papers, 1686-1890
Library of Virginia
28954
96 leaves, photocopies
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Lent for copying by Mrs. Rosemond Taylor Carter, Atlantic, Virginia, 29 April 1976.
Biographical Information
Thomas Teakle Taylor was born 19 October 1775 in Accomack County, Virginia, where he later became a prosperous planter. He married Ann Wharton Williams (13 January 1776-5 December 1845), a widow, on 29 December 1802. They had four children, two of whom lived to adulthood. Thomas T. Taylor died 29 September 1851. His son Edward Wharton Taylor was born 29 September 1803 and also became a prosperous planter. Edward W. Taylor married Mary E. Conquest (1821-1873) 24 April 1844, and they had seven children. Edward W. Taylor died in Accomack County 29 September 1892.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1686-1890, of the Taylor family of Accomack County, Virginia, consisting of accounts, assessments, contracts, correspondence, deeds, genealogies, land surveys, lists, prayers, summonses, tax records, and wills. Wills are of William Taylor, 20 September 1686; John Wharton, 23 February 1814; Calib Brodwater, 18 April 1833; Thomas T. Taylor, 24 June 1851; and Edward Wharton Taylor, 23 October 1888. Deeds are for property sold to John Wharton and to Thomas T. Taylor, both of Accomack County. Correspondence contains a letter, 20 February 1844, from William Ewell to Thomas T. Taylor concerning the renting of his farm; a letter, 3 January 1848, from Taylor to William Mathews concenring the hiring of Fanny, a slave, and Mathews' reply; a leter, 20 May 1884, from Neely and Quinby, attorneys, to Edward W. Taylor concerning his father's will; a letter, 11 April 1890, from Edward W. Taylor to Reverend John Lafferty containing Taylor's boyhood reminiscences; and a letter, 29 April 1890, from Taylor to Robert P. Porter concerning carp in his old mill pond. Accounts consist of Thomas T. Taylor's accounts with Edmund R. Curtis, with J. W. Feddeman and his companies; account of the estate of Thomas T. Taylor, Edward W. Taylor, executor; and account of the estate of William Holland. Tax records include a tax receipt, 1886, and assessments, 1880-1883, of Edward W. Taylor's real and personal property. Papers also include survey, 27 September 1805, of division of land of Joshua Wishart; court summons, 7 July 1830, for Thomas T. and Ann Taylor; contract, 4 June 1877, for lease of land to Old Dominion Steam Company; description of boundary of William S. Mathews' swamp land; a list of slaves; and a prayer by Edward W. Taylor.
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Will, 20 September 1686, of William Taylor, Accomack County, Virginia. Recorded 21 June 1687., 4 leaves, photocopies.
- Deed, 21 April 1795, for 25 acres in Accomack County from Sacker and Tabitha Paerker to John Wharton. Deed recorded 28 September 1795., 3 leaves, photocopies.
- Deed, 1 September 1801, for two tracts of land containing 139 acres and 25 acres in Accomack County from Sacker Parker, William Turpin and Leah Turpin to John Wharton. Includes the consent of Leah Turpin. Deed partially proved 28 September 1801 and recorded 27 June 1803., 5 leaves, photocopies.
- Land survey, 27 September 1805, made by W. P. Evans for divsion of land owned by Joshua Wishart, Accomack County., 2 leaves, photocopies.
- Deed, 23 December 1812, for 236 acres in Accomack County from Joseph Powell and Nancy Powell to John Wharton., 2 leaves, photocopies.
- Consent, 8 January 1813, of Nancy Powell regarding deed dated 23 December 1812 for 236 acres to John Wharton., 1 leaf, photocopy.
- Deed, 22 February 1813, for 424 acres in Accomack County from George and Elizabeth Thomas to John Wharton. Has acknowledgement, 23 February 1813, signed by Elizabeth Thomas. Recorded 27 September 1813., 5 leaves, photocopies.
- Deed, 10 January 1812 [1813?], for 122 acres in Accomack County from Joseph Powell and his wife (Nancy Powell) to John Wharton. Deed partially proved 29 January 1812 [1813?]. Recorded 30 March 1813., 4 leaves, photocopies.
- Will, 23 February 1814, of John Wharton of Accomack County. No recordation date., 2 leaves, photocopies.
- Deed, 24 February 1816, for 98 2/3 acres in Accomack County from Elizabeth Wharton and Bagwell and Catharine Wharton to Thomas T. Taylor. Deed partially proved 24 June 1816 and further proved 30 August 1816. Deed recorded 2 September 1837., 3 leaves, photocopies.
- Deed, 31 May 1821, for 100 acres in Accomack County from Catharine Wharton to Thomas T. Taylor. No recordation date., 3 leaves, photocopies.
- Summons, 7 July 1830, for Thomas T. and Ann Taylor to appear and answer a bill of chancer gainst them and Elizabeth Wharton by David Brodwater. Printed form filled in., 3 leaves, photocopies.
- Deed, January 1832, for 206 acres in Accomack County from Thomas T. Taylor and Nancy [Ann] Taylor to Edward W. Taylor. No recordation date., 2 leaves, photocopies.
- Will, 18 April 1833, of Calib [Caleb] Brodwater [Broadwater], Accomack County. Not recordation date., 2 leaves, photocopies.
- Account, 31 July 1835, of Thomas T. Taylor and Edmund R. Custis., 2 leaves, photocopies.
- Account, February 1840-February 1841, of Thomas T. Taylor with Feddeman and White for clothing., 2 leaves, photocopies.
- Account, 31 December 1842-28 December 1843, of Thomas T. Taylor with J. W. Feddeman for dry-goods and groceries., 2 leaves, photocopies.
- Letter, 20 September 1844, from William Ewell to Thomas T. Taylor stating that he is planning to rent his farm and charge the rent in crops., 2 leaves, photocopies.
- Deed, 28 October 1845, for settlement of legal issues from Francis West, Jr., et al. to Thomas T. Taylor. Recorded 24 November 1845., 5 leaves, photocopies.
- Account, 1845, of Thomas T. Taylor with Feddeman and Conquest., 1 leaf, photocopy.
- Letter, 3 January 1848, from Thomas T. Taylor to William Mathews stating that he is sending Fanny to Mathews to be hired out. Includes Mathews' reply that he will hire her, but thinks she would prefer to work elsewhere., 2 leaves, photocopies.
- Will, 24 June 1851, of Thomas T. Taylor of Accomack County. No recordation date., 3 leaves, photocopies.
- Account, 29 December 1851-16 February 1854, of the estate of Thomas T. Taylor, deceased, in account with Edward W. Taylor. Recorded 12 June 1854., 6 leaves, photocopies.
- Tax receipt, 1856, to Edward W. Taylor. Printed form filled in., 1 leaf, photocopy.
- Contract, 4 June 1877, between Edward W. Taylor, et. al., and N. L. Macready, agent, Old Dominion Steamship Company for lease of 1/8 acre of land., 2 leaves, photocopies.
- Assessment, 1880, 1881, of real and personal property belonging to Edward W. Taylor for taxes., 3 leaves, photocopies.
- Assessment, 1883, of personal property belonging to Edward W. Taylor for taxes., 1 leaf, photocopy.
- Letter, 20 May 1884, from Neely and Quinby, attorneys, Accomack County, to Edward W. Taylor giving their opinion on Thomas T. Taylor's will leaving Edward W. Taylor certain lands., 6 leaves, photocopies.
- Will, 23 October 1888, of Edward W. Taylor of Accomack County. No recordation date., 4 leaves, photocopies.
- Letter, 11 April 1890, from Edward W. Taylor to Reverend John Lafferty concering his life including a description of a religious meeting and a trip to and from Tangier Island, Virginia., 3 leaves, photocopies.
- Letter, 29 April 1890, from Edward W. Taylor to Robert P. Porter concerning carp Taylor had put into his old mill pond., 1 leaf, photocopy.
- Account, n.d., of the estate of William Holland., 2 leaves, photocopies.
- Description, n.d., of boundaries of William S. Mathews' swamp land., 2 leaves, photocopies.
- List, n.d., of slaves., 1 leaf, photocopy.
- Prayer, n.d., written by Edward Taylor., 3 leaves, photocopies.